<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>No Excuses CCIE</title>
 <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2017-03-06T23:21:54-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://bsrandall.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Brian Scott Randall</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>LLDP</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/layer%202/2017/03/06/LLDP/"/>
   <updated>2017-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/layer%202/2017/03/06/LLDP</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;LLDP is the IEEE equivalent of CDP. It’s development was due to Cisco’s deployment of CDP, so the IEEE sought to make a universal version. It is very similar to CDP and many of the Cisco commands for LLDP are the same commands as those for CDP, just substituting lldp for cdp. Like CDP, LLDP is a link layer protocol, but unlike CDP it is specifically for Ethernet networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One additional feature LLDP includes is that LLDP has a TLV for an interface description, so if you set a description with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1#(config-if) description LINK_SW1_SW2&lt;/code&gt;, that description would show up under Switch 2 LLDP like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;SW2# show lldp neighbors detail

Chasis id: 0019.569d.571a
Port id: Fa0/24
Port Description: LINK_SW1_SW2
System Name: SW1.cisco.com
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An enhancement was made to LLDP that allows you to use LLDP for VLAN assignment or POE requirements. This enhanced version is known as LLDP-MED (Media Endpoint Discovery).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CDP Configuration</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/layer%202/2017/03/06/CDP-Configuration/"/>
   <updated>2017-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/layer%202/2017/03/06/CDP-Configuration</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To enable CDP globally we use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cdp run&lt;/code&gt;. To enable CDP on a per-interface basis, use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cdp enable&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;R1#(config) cdp timer seconds&lt;/code&gt;  specifies the frequency of CDP update transmissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;R1#(config) cdp holdtime seconds&lt;/code&gt; specifies the amount of time a receiving device should hold the information sent by your device before discarding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;R1#(config) no cdp adertise-v2&lt;/code&gt; disables the advertisement of CDPv2 advertisements if for some crazy reason you need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;R1#(config) clear cdp counters&lt;/code&gt; resets the traffic counters to zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;R1#(config) clear cdp table&lt;/code&gt; deletes the CDP table of information about neighbors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;R1#(config) show cdp&lt;/code&gt; displays the interval between CDP transmissions, the number of seconds a CDP advertisement is valid for a given port, and the version of the advertisement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;R1#(config) show cdp interface [type number]&lt;/code&gt; displays information about interfaces on which CDP is enabled&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;R1#(config) show cdp entry device-name&lt;/code&gt; displays information about a specific neighbor&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CDP Basics</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/layer%202/2017/03/06/CDP-Basics/"/>
   <updated>2017-03-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/layer%202/2017/03/06/CDP-Basics</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;CDP is a layer 2, Cisco proprietary device discovery protocol. Even though it is a Layer 2 protocol, it provides information about Layer 3 protocols (such as IP address). CDP operates by its member devices sending multicasts to the link-local multicast address 01:00:0c:cc:cc:cc (same as VTP). The member devices listen for multicasts at that address, process them accordingly, and store the information in a local table. The announcements are sent out every 60 seconds by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SNAP (Subnetwork Access Protocol) is required to run CDP, so effectively CDP can run on any data-link protocol that supports SNAP. Ethernet, Frame Relay, and ATM are example medias that support SNAP and thus CDP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDP relays the information about devices by Type-Length-Value (TLV) fields in the CDP packets. The &lt;em&gt;Length&lt;/em&gt; is the length (in bytes) of the Type-Value-Length fields. The Type and Value fields are described below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;type&quot;&gt;Type&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Device ID - 0x0001&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Address - 0x0002&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Port ID - 0x0003&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capabilities - 0x0004&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Version - 0x0005&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Platform - 0x0006&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IP Prefix - 0x0007&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VTP Management Domain - 0x0009 {: .red}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Native VLAN - 0x000a {: .red}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Duplex Status - 0x000b {: .red}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appliance ID - 0x000c {: .red}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Power consumption - 0x0010 {: .red}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;value&quot;&gt;Value&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Device ID - MAC address in ASCII or the FQDN&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Address&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Port ID - ASCII string that names the port from which the message was sent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capabilities - has a value describing the device capabilities:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;0x01 - level 3 routing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;0x02 - level 2 transparent bridging&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;0x04 - level 2 source-route bridging&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;0x08 - level 2 switching not running Spanning Tree&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;0x10 - sends and receives packets for a network layer protocol&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;0x20 - the device does not forward IGMP reports&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;0x40 - level 1 function&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Version - software version running the device&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Platform - ASCII string describing the device (e.g. Cisco 7000)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IP Prefix - a set of 0 or more IP Prefixes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switches see the MAC multicast address used by CDP as a special address and will not forward it out of other interfaces on a switch. Routers do not forward layer 2 frames out of their interfaces ever, so therefore only directly connected neighbors receive the CDP advertisement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of CDP is that if you walk into a network and you do not know the topology, you can use CDP to quickly learn the entire layout of the network (as long as all the devices are Cisco!).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MultiChassis EtherChannel</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/27/EtherChannel-MultiChassis/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/27/EtherChannel-MultiChassis</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A LAG bundle to the same access switch results in Fate Sharing for the links in the bundle. The alternative is to break the links out of the LAG, and have the NICs of a server connect to two different access switches. But by breaking the LAG, we now have half the available bandwidth for the server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With MultiChassis EtherChannel, we trick the server into running LAG between two different access switches. There are multiple ways to do this using different protocols made by different vendors. We generically call it MLAG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protocol must take a physical triangle as seen below, and make it into a logical point-to-point. Many problems arise that the protocol must deal with. If NIC A sends traffic to Switch A, Switch A must know not to send that to Switch B, or else a loop might form.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.cisco.com/c/dam/en/us/td/i/200001-300000/220001-230000/226001-227000/226936.eps/_jcr_content/renditions/226936.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
The protocols are so customized, that different platforms from the same vendor cannot even run MLAG. The control place has to be identical. Cisco therefore has a couple of implementations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stackwise Cross-Stack EtherChannel&lt;/em&gt; has control plane over dedicated stacking cables. These stack cables create a bidirectional closed loop as seen below. One control plane is shared amongst members as well as one management plane. So if you were to log into one switch, you are actually viewing the configuration for the stack. This is used on the Access Platforms such as Catalyst 3750/3850. StackWise can have more than 2 members, up to the stack limit
&lt;img src=&quot;https://encrypted-tbn1.gstatic.com/images?q=tbn:ANd9GcRguQ7GRPRoSYAmPfJ4MCMN2r160qFDougT6yyluxFXu6n42Foxgg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Virtual Switching System (VSS)&lt;/em&gt; is used on the aggregation platforms such as Catalyst 4500/6500/6800. VSS is similar to Stackwise as there is one management plane and one control plane shared between connected switches. Typically with VSL, the links are going to be 2x10G LAG. VSS switches are udeployed in pairs and will usually have 1 active supervisor and 3 standby supervisors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Virtual Port Channel (vPC)&lt;/em&gt; is very similar to VSS but it runs on the Data Center platforms such as Nexus 5000/7000/9000. The control plane is synchronized over a vPC Peer Link, which are typically 2x10GigE LAG. The biggest difference between vPC and VSS, is that vPC has &lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt; independent control planes and &lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt; independent management planes. vPC like VSS is deployed in pairs.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>EtherChannel PaGP</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/26/EtherChannel-PAgP/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/26/EtherChannel-PAgP</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Port Aggregation Protocol (PAgP) is a Cisco proprietary protocol that is only supported on Cisco switches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two modes of PAgP are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;auto: places a port into a passive negotiating state&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;desirable: places a port into active negotiating state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Layer 2 EtherChannels, the first port that comes up lends its MAC address to the EtherChannel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PAgP supports up to 8 Ethernet ports of the same type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all EtherChannels (including on and PAgP), when a group is first created, all ports follow the parameters set for the first port to be added to the group. If you change the configuration of any of these parameters, you must also make changes to all ports in the group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allowed-VLAN list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spanning-tree path cost for each VLAN&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spanning-tree port priority for each VLAN&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spanning-tree Port Fast setting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all Layer 2 EtherChannels, if the ports are access ports they must all be in the same VLAN.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>EtherChannel Load-Balancing</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/26/EtherChannel-Load-Balancing/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/26/EtherChannel-Load-Balancing</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The balancing method is locally significant and outbound. So it is OK for one side of a LAG to be src-MAC and the other side to be dest-IP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To configure the load-balancing method by using the&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;port-channel load-balance&lt;/code&gt; global configuration command. EtherChannel load-balancing can use MAC Address or IP address, source or destination address, or both source and destination address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The selected load balancing mode applies to all ether channels on a switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With source-MAC address forwarding, packets are distributed across the ports based on the source-MAC of the &lt;em&gt;incoming&lt;/em&gt; packet. So packets from the same host use the same port in the channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With destination-MAC address forwarding, packets are distributed across the ports of the channel based on the destination-MAC of the incoming packet. So packets destined to the same host use the same port in the channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With source-and-destination MAC address forwarding, packets are distributed across the ports in a channel based on both the source and the destination MAC address. This is often used if it is not clear whether source-MAC or destination-MAC would be more appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IP based forwarding has the same principles as the MAC based forwarding outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To chose the appropriate load-balancing method, you must analyze the position of the EtherChannel in the network. For example, if you have 4 hosts going towards one router, you would be much better load-balancing based on source-MAC  than destination-MAC from the switch. On the router, you will be better off using destination-MAC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To configure EtherChannel load-balancing, in global config use the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;`port-channel load-balance {dst-ip | dst-mac | src-dst-ip | src-dst-mac | src-ip | src-mac}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;`
The default is src-mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One negative of EtherChannel is that flows cannot exceed the bandwidth of an individual link. EtherChannel adds lanes to the highway but it doesn’t increase the speed limit.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>EtherChannel LACP</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/24/EtherChannel-LACP/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/24/EtherChannel-LACP</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;LACP is the IEEE standard for establishing a single logical channel out of several physical ports. It is popular as it can be used in mixed-vendor switch environments. LACP ensures that when an EtherChannel is created, all physical members all have the same speed, duplex, link-type, and VLAN information. LACP is a control protocol for LAG. The official name is IEEE 802.3ad Link Aggregation (LAG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LACP supports up to 16 Ethernet ports of the same type. Up to eight ports can be active, and up to eight ports can be in standby mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LACP assigns system priority, port priority, and and an administrative key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;System priority&lt;/em&gt; and the MAC address form the System ID. Between two LACP neighbors, the switch with the lowest System ID will be the decision maker using the LACP Port Priority&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Port priority&lt;/em&gt; and the port number form the port identifier. The switch uses the port identifier to decide which ports to put in standby mode when a hardware limitation prevents all ports from aggregating. Port priority is also used when more than 8 physical ports are put into a channel group. Port priority will decide which 8 ports will be the active ports in the etherchannel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Administrative key&lt;/em&gt; defines the capabilities of a port to aggregate with other ports, based on the port’s physical characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample Configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;SW1# interface range GigabitEthernet0/1-2
SW1# channel-group 1 mode active
SW1# exit
SW1# interface port-channel 1
SW1# switchport trunk encapsulation dot1q
SW1# switchport mode trunk
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;SW2# interface range GigabitEthernet0/1-2
SW2# channel-group 1 mode active
SW2# exit
SW2# interface port-channel 1
SW2# switchport trunk encapsulation dot1q
SW2# switchport mode trunk
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also start with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;interface port-channel 1&lt;/code&gt; command and then define the channel group. For Layer 3 ether channel, you would want to define the port-channel first and then issue the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;no switchport&lt;/code&gt; interface command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;interface port-channel 1&lt;/code&gt; is the logical interface. The channel-group command binds the logical interface to a physical port. The port-channel interface (numbered 1 - 48) correspond to the one specified with the channel-group interface configuration command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A successful Layer 2 EtherChannel will show SU with the command &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show etherchannel summary&lt;/code&gt;. An unsuccessful layer 2 will show SD.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MST IST-CIST</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/mst/2017/02/23/MST-IST-CIST/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/mst/2017/02/23/MST-IST-CIST</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;IST is the Internal Spanning Tree, also known as instance 0. This instance is designated to carry all STP information, including information from other instances. MSTP does not send BPDUs for ever instance separately - these are all contained within the IST BPDU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accommodate, the other instances information is carried within the IST BPDU using special M-Record fields - one for every active MSTI. These fields carry carry MSTP information such as bridge priority, root path cost, and port priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IST also plays a huge role in multiple MSTP region configurations. When a switch receives a BPDU from another region, it marks the corresponding port as MSTP &lt;em&gt;boundary&lt;/em&gt;. The interconnected, different region switches then form a CIST spanning across the regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blog.ine.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/mstp-3-multi-region-physical-topology.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, an IST is internal to a region while a CIST is the IST spanning across multiple regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a sample MST BPDU:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blog.ine.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/mstp-3-multi-region-cst-mstp-packet-format.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CIST Root is elected among all regions while the CIST Regional Root is elected in every region. The IST Root = CIST Regional Root in cases where multiple MST regions interoperate. The CIST Root is the bridge that has the lowest Bridge Id among all regions - the CIST Root could be a bridge inside a region or a boundary switch in a region. The CIST Regional Root is a &lt;em&gt;boundary switch&lt;/em&gt; elected for every region based on the shortest external path cost to reach the CIST Root. As mentioned above, it is important to remember that the CIST Regional Root becomes the root of the IST for the given region as well - the region changes its IST election process to make the CIST Regional Root the IST root.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an MST switch boots up, it declares itself the CIST Root and CIST Regional Root and announce that it its outgoing BPDUs on all internal ports. On boundary ports (those that have received BPDUs from another region), the switch will only advertise its CIST Root Bridge ID and CIST External Root Path Cost, hiding the details of the region’s inner topology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region that contains the CIST Root automatically places all of its boundary ports in an unblocked state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;CIST External Root Path Cost&lt;/em&gt; is the cost to reach the CIST Root across the links connecting the boundary ports. When a BPDU is received on an internal link, this cost is not changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only a boundary switch can be elected as the CIST Regional Root, and this is the switch with the lowest cost to reach the CIST Root. If a boundary switch receives a BPDU with a lower CIST External Root Path cost on one of its internal ports, it will stop announcing itself as the CIST Regional Root and start announcing the new metric out of its boundary ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a switch is a CIST Regional Root, it elects one of its boundary ports as the CIST Root port and blocks all other boundary ports. If a boundary switch is not the CIST Regional Root, it will mark its boundary ports as Designated or Alternate, Designate only if it has a better External Root Path cost or in case of a tie, lower CIST Regional Root Bridge ID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regional MSTIs are constructed independently at every region, but they have to be mapped to the CIST at the boundary ports. This equates to the inability to load-balance VLAN traffic on the boundary links by mapping VLANs to different instances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A topology change in the CST could change all paths in the topology thus requiring massive MAC address relearning.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>EtherChannel</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/23/EtherChannel-General/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/etherchannel/2017/02/23/EtherChannel-General</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;LAG goal is to trick our Spanning Tree Protocol into forwarding active/active across multiple links. The risk we take is an infinite loop in the data plane, as there is no TTL with Ethernet. The LAG negotiation protocols help to mitigate this risk. Static LAG is supported but not recommended, as a failure to LAG can cause an STP Loop. If you do deploy Static LAG, it is recommended to deploy EtherChannel Guard to help mitigate the chances of a loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PAgP and LACP accomplish the exact same thing, just in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since both PAgP and LACP both require the member ports to have the same characteristics, a good command to start with is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show interfaces status&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>VTP Pruning</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/vtp/2017/02/22/VTP-Pruning/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/vtp/2017/02/22/VTP-Pruning</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The principal of VTP pruning is if a client sends a broadcast to its connected switch’s access port, that switch will flood the broadcast to all other connected switches in the VTP / Layer 2 domain. Because of VTP, all the other switches would be aware of the client VLAN, and would thus be required to flood the broadcast to all other switches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if the other switches do not have any clients connected to access ports in that VLAN? They are still having to process the request, and the network segment still has to bear the broadcast traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you enable VTP pruning, you are enabling it for the entire VTP domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NEED TO FINISH&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Multiple Spanning Tree</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/mst/2017/02/22/MST/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/mst/2017/02/22/MST</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Multiple Spanning Tree (MST) was developed to overcome the high resource requirements of PVST. In reality, there are only a few logical redundant design on a network, regardless of the number of VLANs or the number of physical links. With MST you can run several different logical topologies (instances), and map VLANs to those instances. You get the benefit of running a redundant, fully utilized network without the resource overhead on the switches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the end result is that with PVST, a port is either forwarding or discarding for a VLAN, while with MST, a port is either forwarding or discarding for an instance which contains multiple VLANs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MST is defined by IEEE 802.1s. A special instance, instance 0 or the Internal Spanning Tree (IST), is designated to carry all STP information. The BPDUs for IST carry all the standard RSTP information, as well as the configuration name, revision number, and a &lt;em&gt;hash value&lt;/em&gt; calculated over the VLAN to instance mapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should not run MSTP on access ports.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>VTP Versions</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/vtp/2017/02/21/VTP-Versions/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/vtp/2017/02/21/VTP-Versions</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;VTP is a Cisco proprietary protocol that allows VLAN administration to be shared across switches. It gives an administrator the capability to centrally administer VLAN creation across one or two switches, and have those VLANs propagate across a VTP domain made up of any number of switches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 versions of VTP, versions 1, 2, and 3.  There are not many significant changes between versions 1 and 2, except version 2 introduced support for Token Ring VLANs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Version 3 introduced the following enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hidden authentication (does not appear in plain text in the configuration file)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extended VLAN support. Versions 1 and 2 only support VLANs 1 - 1000 only.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for private VLANs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for MST&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>VTP Messages</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/vtp/2017/02/21/VTP-Header/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/vtp/2017/02/21/VTP-Header</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;All VTP packets contain these fields in the header:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VTP version (1, 2, or 3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VTP Message Type
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Summary advertisements&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Subset advertisement&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Advertisement requests&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;VTP Join Messages&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Management domain length&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Management domain name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most VTP packets contain the &lt;em&gt;configuration revision number&lt;/em&gt; of the sender. This is used to determine if the received information is more recent than the current version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, &lt;em&gt;summary advertisements&lt;/em&gt; are sent every 5 minutes. The summary advertisement contains the VTP domain name and the current configuration revision number. If the VTP domain matches the switch’s configured VTP domain, and the configuration revision number is higher than its own revision, the switch will send an &lt;em&gt;advertisement request&lt;/em&gt;. Otherwise, it ignores the packet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;summary-advertisement-packet-format&quot;&gt;Summary Advertisement Packet Format&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.cisco.com/c/dam/en/us/support/docs/lan-switching/vtp/10558-21c.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;subset advertisement&lt;/em&gt; will follow a summary advertisement - it is the message that actually contains a list (or a subset of a list) of the VLANs being advertised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A switch will send an &lt;em&gt;advertisement request&lt;/em&gt; in these situations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the switch has been reset&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the VTP domain name has been changed on the switch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the switch has received a VTP summary advertisement with a higher configuration than its own&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dot1q</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/21/Dot1q/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/21/Dot1q</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;trunks&quot;&gt;Trunks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dot1q is the standard trunking protocol used for transporting multiple VLANs across a trunk port. A trunk is a point-to-point link that carries the traffic for multiple VLANs across a single trunk. Dot1q is a standard that tags VLANs for identification. The receiving switch will then strip the VLAN tag from the frame before passing it to the appropriate access port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full name for Dot1q is IEEE 802.1Q.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 802.1Q Tagged frame looks like this:
&lt;img src=&quot;http://bsrandall.github.io/public/img/802.1q.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The PRI field is the 3-bit 802.1p priority field.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The CFI field is always set to 0 for Ethernet switches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VLAN ID is a 12-bit field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the extra fields, an 802.1Q frame has an MTU of 1522 bytes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a non-802.1Q enabled device or an access port receives a tagged frame, it simply ignores the frame and forwards it as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;native-vlan&quot;&gt;Native VLAN&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Native VLAN on a trunk is the VLAN to which untagged traffic belongs. Across a trunk, the Native VLANs should match on each end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# show interface trunk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;will show the Native VLAN for each interface that has active trunking.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dynamic Trunking Protocol (DTP)</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/21/DTP/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/21/DTP</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dynamic Trunking Protocol is a Cisco proprietary protocol that, when configured, attempts to negotiate trunking between two connected ports. It will try to negotiate trunking as well as the encapsulation type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# switchport mode dynamic auto&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allows the interfaces to become a trunk if the neighboring trunk is set to trunk or desirable mode&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this is the default setting for newer Cisco switches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if both ends of a trunk are set to dynamic auto, they will not form a trunk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# switchport mode dynamic desireable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;makes the interface actively attempt to negotiate trunking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the link will become a trunk if the neighbor interface is set to trunk, auto, or desirable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# switchport nonegotiate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prevents the interface from sending DTP frames&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can use this when the interface switch port mode is &lt;em&gt;access&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;trunk&lt;/em&gt; only&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if enabled, to establish a trunk the neighbor interface must be manually set to &lt;em&gt;trunk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>VLANs</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/21/Allowed-VLANs/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/21/Allowed-VLANs</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;By default, all VLANs are allowed to traverse an 802.1Q trunk once it is active. To restrict which VLANs are allowed to cross a trunk, you must go into IOS and explicitly define the VLANs that are allowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# switchport trunk allow VLAN 15-20,22,25&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# switchport trunk allowed vlan add 27&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# switchport trunk allowed vlan remove 18&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must remember that if an allowed VLAN list is already configured on a trunk, issuing the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# switchport trunk allowed vlan 16-20,2,25&lt;/code&gt; command will overwrite the previously defined VLANs. You must use the &lt;em&gt;add&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;remove&lt;/em&gt; commands if there is already an allowed clan configuration in the running config.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Access Ports</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/21/Access-Ports/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/21/Access-Ports</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Access ports are those ports that are connected to end devices, not other switches. We define an access port on the command line with 
SW1# switchport mode access&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will see later with Spanning Tree, that PortFast can and should be used on access ports. This does two things. First, it allows the port to skip the listening phase for faster availability. Second, it prevents the access port from sending TCNs (Topology Change Notifications) every time a user plugs or unplugs a device into the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another Spanning Tree feature which will relate to Access ports is BPDU Guard. With BPDU Guard, if the switch receives a BPDU on a port where BPDU Guard was enabled, the port will transition to the errdisabled state.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>VLANs</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/20/VLANs/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/vlan/2017/02/20/VLANs</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;standard-vlans&quot;&gt;Standard VLANs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cisco calls VLANS 1 - 1005 Normal VLANs. Of those, VLAN 1 is the Cisco default. You can use this VLAN, but your are not allowed to delete it. VLANs 1002 - 1005 are the Cisco defaults for FDDI and Token Ring. These also cannot be deleted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That leaves us VLANs 2 - 1001 as Normal VLANs that we can add or delete as we wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VLANs 2 - 1001 are pruning eligible, while VLANs 1006 - 4094 are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you delete a VLAN, any LAN ports configured as access ports for that VLAN become inactive until you assign them to a new VLAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;extended-vlans&quot;&gt;Extended VLANs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extended VLANs are in the range of 1006 - 4094. Extended range VLANs are not controlled by VTP and cannot be pruned. The router must be in VTP transparent mode in order to create extended VLANs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extended range VLANs are not stored in van.dat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;vlan-database&quot;&gt;VLAN Database&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only applies to standard VLANs.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hello World</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/general/2017/02/20/Hello-World/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/general/2017/02/20/Hello-World</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first post in my newly launched blog. I decided to go with Jekyll and a GitHub page for my blog backend. I wanted my content to be in Markdown, as that seems to be the authoring flavor of the day. Jekyll and GitHub just made sense due to their support of Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our knowledge is at its pinnacle when we can fluidly explain topics to others. That is my main motivation for this blog. There most likely will not be any ground breaking content, but I hope to explain some of the topics in a way that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other two benefits to my blog is hopefully improving on my Markdown and typing skills. It is sad that I still type as badly as I do, considering how much I type. I will use Markdown highlighting for code samples. TextExpander should make all of this a little easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is some sample IOS commands using Markdown:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# switchport trunk encapsulation dot1q&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SW1# switchport mode trunk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I am off to the races. Or as most of those who have gone before me stress, off to start the marathon!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Git</title>
   <link href="http://bsrandall.github.io/general/2017/02/20/Git/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://bsrandall.github.io/general/2017/02/20/Git</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am not a git master, nor do I strive to become one. But I do need to know some basic details to manage this blog as well as my INE VIRL configurations. There are probably better ways to do this, but for my purposes, these are the commands I am running to push my updates from my MacBook to by GitHub page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/Dropbox/jekyll.bsrandall.github.io(master) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; git add --all&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; ~/Dropbox/jekyll.bsrandall.github.io(master) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; git commit -m &quot;update notes&quot;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/Dropbox/jekyll.bsrandall.github.io(master) &amp;gt;&amp;gt; git push -u origin master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
